A Guide to the Burton N. Harrison Papers, 1864-1866
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Burton N. Harrison Papers, 1864-1866
The Library of Virginia
44265
36 pages and 3 leaves (16 items)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from State Records, The Library of Virginia, Richmond 23219.
Biographical Information
Burton N. Harrison was born 14 July 1838 to Jesse and Francis Braud Harrison Burton of New Orleans, Louisiana. He attended the University of Mississippi and graduated from Yale University in 1859, where he edited the Yale Literary Magazine. In February 1862 he became the private secretary to Jefferson Davis and served in that capacity until the end of the war. In 1866 he moved to New York and was admitted to the New York Supreme Court bar. He married Constance Cary on 26 November 1867. In 1875 he became secretary and counsel of New York City's Rapid Transit Commission. He died 29 March 1904 in Washington, DC.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1864-1866, of Burton N. Harrison, while serving as private secretary to Jefferson Davis, concerning the Hampton Roads Peace Conference that took place 3 February 1865 near Fort Monroe, Newport News, Virginia. The letters were all copied by Harrison from original correspondence in his possession and each letter is noted as such, often with additional information, by Harrison. Correspondents include Jefferson Davis, Frank P. Blair, Abraham Lincoln, Alexander Stephens, John A. Campbell, and R.M.T. Hunter. An itemized list of letters in the collection is included [Item 1] and each letter has a corresponding alphabetical delineation. It is possible that the letters were used for an exhibit at the Library of Virginia.
The first letter, 30 June 1866, from Harrison to Mr. Reed [possibly William B. Reed, Chestnut Hill, Pennsylvania] explains the significance of the letters regarding the "Blair case" and the Hampton Roads Peace Conference. Harrison sent the letters to Mr. Reed so that he may have the 'whole record' of the efforts of Frank P. Blair and wanted Reed's opinion on how the papers 'bear him [Blair] out." Harrison also comments on Blair's meetings with President Lincoln and personal correspondence with Varina Davis.
The initial correspondence, 1864 December-1865 January, between Frank P. Blair and Jefferson Davis; and Blair and Abraham Lincoln, details Blair's proposal to initiate a delegation to discuss terms to end the war. In the letters, 30 January and 1 February 1865, Confederate agents Alexander Stephens, John A. Campbell, and R.M.T. Hunter, ask permission of General U.S. Grant to visit Washington, D.C. to confer with President Lincoln. The letters, 1-2 February 1865, also from Stephens, Campbell, and Hunter, to Major Thomas Eckert, additionally request passage into Washington, D.C. and alternatively offer to meet in another location if necessary. The final letter, 5 February 1865, from Stephens, Campbell, and Hunter, to Jefferson Davis, details the meeting with President Lincoln and William Seward including the refusal of Lincoln to accept any terms that allowed for Confederate independence or the continuance of slavery.
Contents List
- Item listing [for possible exhibit]. (Folder 1, Folio 1)
- Letter, Burton N. Harrison, New York, to [William B. Reed], 1866 June 30. (Folder 1, Folio 2)
- Letter, Frank P. Blair, Headquarters Armies of the United States, to Jefferson Davis, 1864 December 30. (Folder 1, Folio A)
- Letter, Frank P. Blair, Headquarters Armies of the United States, to Jefferson Davis, 1864 December 30. (Folder 1, Folio B)
- Memo of a confidential conversation between Frank P. Blair and Jefferson Davis, 1865 January 12. (Folder 1, Folio C)
- Letter, Jefferson Davis, Richmond, Virginia, to Frank P. Blair, 1865 January 12. (Folder 1, Folio D)
- Letter, Abraham Lincoln, Washington, DC, to Frank P. Blair, 1865 January 18. (Folder 1, Folio E)
- Letter, Frank P. Blair, Richmond, Virginia, to Jefferson Davis, 1865 January 22. (Folder 1, Folio F)
- Letter, Frank P. Blair, to Jefferson Davis, 1865 January 25. (Folder 1, Folio G)
- Letter, Abraham Lincoln, Washington, DC, to Frank P. Blair, 1865 January 18. (Folder 1, Folio H)
- Letter, Jefferson Davis, Richmond, Virginia, to John A. Campbell, 1865 January 28. (Folder 1, Folio H)
- Letter, Alexander Stephens, John A. Campbell, and R.M.T. Hunter, Petersburg, Virginia, to General U.S. Grant, 1865 January 30. (Folder 1, Folio I)
- Letter, Alexander Stephens, John A. Campbell, and R.M.T. Hunter, City Point, Virginia, to General U.S. Grant, 1865 February 1. (Folder 1, Folio K)
- Letter, Alexander Stephens, John A. Campbell, and R.M.T. Hunter, City Point, Virginia, to Major Thomas C. Eckert, 1865 February 2. (Folder 1, Folio L)
- Letter, Alexander Stephens, John A. Campbell, and R.M.T. Hunter, City Point, Virginia, to Major Thomas C. Eckert, 1865 February 1. (Folder 1, Folio M)
- Letter, Alexander Stephens, John A. Campbell, and R.M.T. Hunter, Richmond, Virginia, to Jefferson Davis, 1865 February 5. (Folder 1, Folio 3)